hello everyone
welcome to the video lecture series of
data structure
our today's topic is introduction to
array
and wendy error representation of
memory and 2d array representation and
we will also see
about the how to calculate the memory
address for
one directive myself janisha
your instructor so let's start
with the outlines see however
today's outlines are the first
we'll gonna see about the array
then memory representation in array then
one day example memory representation of
2d8 so students now it's time
to tell me that what do you mean by the
array
students error is nothing but is a
collection of homogeneous
elements where each and every elements
are stored in a sequential memory
okay so when the elements are stored in
a sequential manner
and in the continuous form in the memory
then
that is known as an m so here i am just
showing you one example
that whatsapp what do you mean by the
homogeneous homogeneous means students
the same
type and elements here stored in a
continuous
fashion here in array index starts from
0 make sure then
let's go ahead syntax that's
how to define an array so students we
can define an
array like first we need to write data
type
then array name then science
data type can be integer float character
animal and a name should be meaningful
make sure
if you want to make an array of students
then just give it a name like
std student or students fine
and in square brackets we are writing
the size of the array
size of the array like 5 10
anything so if i want to declare an
array of size 10 of integer type
then it can be like example integer
a double r of 10. fine
now let's go ahead see our the next
topic
is memory representation in 1d
so students here you can see that
the integer array of 5
students if i am taking the elements of
array with size 5 then it is like a
integer a of 5
so integer a contains 5 elements
elements are like this
you can see in this figure like 10 20 30
40 and 50
so as you know the array stored in a
continuous memory
allocations so if my first element
address is 1000 then the next
can be implemented as per the size is
such like if this is our array of
integer type
so the next element size can be two byte
incremented like one double 0 2 1
0 4 6 8 such like this so
the first element of array is
known as a of 0 here our variable name
is
a and the element situated at index
0 that's why the first element is
a of 0 fine so in green color you can
see
the array indices in the brown color you
can see like the
array addresses okay fine now
the next students a of 0
a of 0 is about the first element
which is also known as the base element
fine because ls starts from a of 0
now the element stored at a of 0 is 10
and address of a of 0 is 1000
next element addresses 1 0 2 which is
age of 1 so students here you can easily
say that
if my the array is of integer type then
the elements can be implemented the
address can be implemented in two bytes
but what happens if i have the floating
type of panel
students if you have a floating type of
array
then your addresses can be incremented
four bytes like a of zero is at one
thousand
then a of one can be at one double zero
four one double zero eight
one is one zero one two okay now
what about the base address whatever the
address of the first element is known as
base address make it clear the an
address of the first element of the
array is known as
base address here the base address is
thousand
now the base address address of the
first
a of zero address is thousand now how
many memory occupied by this
students the total memory occupied by
this whole
a array is 10 minutes
why because there are five elements are
there each and every element
of type integer and integer contains two
bytes
so that becomes 10 max so
if the array is of protein type then the
memory
can be 5 into 4 which is equal to 20
bytes
fine so now let's start with the memory
calculation
or example of only f
students here you can see the calculate
the question is like this
to calculate the address of element
in single dimensional error fine
students formula for that to calculate
the address of
element in single dimensional array is
air phi is equal to
base address b a briefly see
a of phi is equal to base address b
s stands for this address plus i minus
l star size star that means
multiplication do not forget that
so i that means index which
on which the address we want to find it
out then
l l means lower bound okay so what do
you mean by the lower one
students if we have an array of size
five
then index starts from zero that's why
the elements goes like this
a of zero one two three and four
so the zero is known as zero is known as
lower bound of the array
and four is known as upper bound of the
array
fine so now just the i is index
b a that means less address l that means
lower amount
and the total number of elements are in
the array is
u minus l plus 1 just make sure
what c please focus on this formula
that u minus l plus 1 q means upper
bound
l means lower bound plus 1 that is the
total size of the elements in
error fine so let's start with the
example
the question is calculate the address of
a of 6
calculate the address of a of 6 if
the given array is a of 9 so
here we have the total size of the
elements
a of 9 arrays a of 9 so total 9 elements
are there
fine what we need to find it out we need
to find
out the address of a of 6 so
our i becomes 6 students base address is
also given
base address is 1000 and the array is of
integer type l so just put
all the given data into the elements
such like the first one is i i is equal
to 6
size of the array is 9 okay fine
then the base address is thousand and
what exactly size
size id this size is known as size of
the element not array fine here
the size of the element is two bytes
just because it is of type and integer
type an error
fine so size is equal to 2 and array is
a of 9
so students in a of 9 array the element
starts from index 0
and upper bound is a so l is equal to
0 and u is equal to 8 fine
so next is to put these values in the
formula
the formula is a of i is equal to base
address plus i minus l multiply by size
base address is 1000 i see l
zero obviously lower bound is zero then
size is equal to two so our answer is
one zero
six two another question is that that
how many total elements are there
you can easily find it out with the
formula u minus
l plus 1 or in this you can easily get
it that nine elements are there but
how can we get it from the formula upper
bound students
upper bound is
forgot students upper bound is
8 minus l is 0
plus 1 so 8 plus 1 becomes 9
so here 9 elements are there now i am
taking the next
example next example is the calculate
the address of elements in single
dimensional error
example 2 c must create the question
first
the question is calculate the address of
m of minus 3
m of minus 3 where the array is
m of minus 9 dot dot dot 7
students here m of minus 9 triple dot 7
this is the range of the array indexes
range of
either array indexes minus 9 is a lower
amount
and 7 is the upper part so make sure
that here this minus 9 and 7 is not this
two dimensional array but it shows the
single dimensional array but the range
of
indexes fine so here we need to find out
the address of
m of minus 3 the given array is m of
minus 9
to 7 minus 9 dot dot dot 7
that means minus 9 to 7 with the base
address one double zero
two fine so it can be a floating type
array
students the array type is also given
it's a floating type error
okay also calculate the number of
elements in array
so we need to also calculate the number
of elements in the error
so in this question students we have
each and every data
just put it down in the elements
formula formula is total number of
elements are in array u minus l plus 1
u minus l plus 1 which is equal to
like 7 minus minus 9 plus 1
7 minus 1 minus 9 plus 1 it becomes 70
so here you can see that there are 17
elements are there
17 elements are there fine i is equal to
what do you mean by the i i is equal to
minus 3 because we need to find the
address of m of minus 3
okay lower bound lower bound is minus
nine upper bound
is seven and size is
four fine so just put this whole thing
into the formula
the formula is a of i is equal to base
address
plus i minus l multiplied by
sine a of phi that means m of minus
m of minus three so m of minus three
is equal to base address students base
address is one double zero two
so one number zero two plus i
i that means minus 3 minus minus l
3 minus 3 minus minus 9 calculating this
sum solve it and you get the answer 1 0
2 6. so students one zero two six
is our address of the element m of minus
three
now go ahead the next topic is memory
representation of
today this is our last topic of today's
lecture
okay first how can you define or how can
you write the 2d array you can write it
like this
integer a of 3 3 in teacher a of 3 3 it
means
data type then variable name then
size of row 10 size of column so
here integer a of 33 it means it is a
two dimensional
array so a is a two dimensional m
students here see
this table or this matrices this matrix
is nothing but it's a two dimensional
array i am just showing you how can i
represent these two dimensional array
matrices
into the memory fine the first element
at 0 0 is at
10 then 20 10 30 so
10 20 30 then 40 50 60
70 89 so here three cross three matrix
total we have nine
elements fine so now what next
students we can store the data or we can
represent the 2d area in memory
with two different ways the first way is
row major
okay what do you mean by row major
students this
representation of data is known as
promising
in rhodometer we are just inserting the
element provides
okay so just say this 10 to 90 i'm just
writing the string
from 10 to 90 and then what happens
what happens 10 the address is 10 is
c first element is 10
which is known as a of 0 0 the next is
20 which is a of 0 1
third will become a of 0 2 so when you
are just inserting the data according to
the row bytes
then it becomes roommate here
are the column major
the column widget data are inserted such
like this in column measure the data
elements are inserted
column bytes but if we just considering
the column
data for this particular matrixes then
the data elements are four column
measure like
trend 40 70 then
20 50 80 10 30
69 so such like this students we are
just inserting the data in the memory
according to the column bytes so what
will become the
indexes for that see now 10
after that i'm just writing 40 see our
after that i'm writing 40 after that i'm
writing
70 because this is a column major
not row major fine so the next is
what do you mean by the rev measure room
with the students it means
no matter here the elements are stored
according to
robots in column meter the elements are
stored
according to the column twice so
students in this lecture we
learn about the array introduction of
the array
then how can we represent the elements
in 1d array
and 2dm we have also seen the examples
of only array that how can we calculate
the memory address
in 1d so if you have
any doubt in this lecture then please
feel free to ask me
thank you so much